Okay, today's דף *Daf* is פ"ח *Peh-Chet*, we pick up on from
ס"ח עמוד ב' *Samach-Chet Amud Bet* of a משנה mishna *Mishnah* where
we are a little bit behind, but we God-willing will catch up
in there before. We'll be there again. So let's take a look.
So we dealt with the question on the איסור issur *Issur* of
חדש chadash... *Chadash* and is it דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* דרבנן *d'Rabbanan* nowadays and
now we get to this nice משנה mishna *Mishnah* that discusses not
only the עומר Omer *Omer* but the שתי הלחם shtei halechem? *Shtei
Halechem* and how they work together. So let's take a look. העומר
היה מתיר matir במדינה ושתי הלחם במקדש *Ha'omer haya matir bamedina v'Shtei
Halechem bamigdash*. So the עומר Omer *Omer* would make the new grain
permissible outside and the שתי הלחם shtei halechem *Shtei Halechem* outside in
the general, you know, country, outside of the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* and
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem *Shtei Halechem* would allow the new grain
to be brought in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beis Hamikdash*. Some
people are under the misconception that because the עומר Omer *Omer* comes
from barley and the שתי הלחם shtei halechem *Shtei Halechem* comes from
wheat, that the עומר Omer *Omer* permitted the barley and the שתי
הלחם shtei halechem *Shtei Halechem* permitted the wheat. That's not true. The
עומר Omer *Omer* permits all grain. ולחם וקלי וכרמל לא תאכלו עד
עצם היום הזה עד הביאכם את קרבן korban אלהיכם *V'lechem v'kali v'karmel
lo sochlu ad etzem hayom haze ad havi'achem et korban elokeichem*. So
what does the שתי הלחם shtei halechem *Shtei Halechem* do? Well, you
could have said it doesn't permit anything, you could have said the
שתי הלחם shtei halechem. *Shtei Halechem* is just a קרבן korban *korban*,
you know, a way of giving thanks to God on, you know,
like ביכורים bikkurim *Bikkurim* is a קרבן korban, *korban*, a way of
giving thanks to God on שבועות Shavuot *Shavuos*, but חז"ל *Chazal* understand
that because it's called ביכורים bikkurim *Bikkurim*,
in order to give it that status of ביכורים Bikkurim. *Bikkurim*, it
can only, it must be the first קרבן *korban* in the מקדש
Mikdash *Mikdash* of the new grain. Now technically of course it's not.
The first קרבן *korban* in the מקדש Mikdash, *Mikdash* of the new
grain was the עומר Omer *Omer*. But forgetting the עומר Omer *Omer*,
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem *Shtei Halechem* was the first קרבן *korban*
of the new grain and no קרבן *korban* can be brought in
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beis Hamikdash* of the new grain until
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem *Shtei Halechem* is brought. So that this
משנה mishna *Mishnah* articulates that it was מתיר matir. *matir*, that it
was מתיר matir, במקדש *matir b'mikdash*. אין In, מביאין מנחות Menachot, וביכורים
ומנחת בהמה קודם לעומר *Ein mevi'in menachot u'bikurim u'minchat behemah kodem la'omer*.
One should not bring a normal מנחה minchah *mincha* or ביכורים Bikkurim.
*Bikkurim*, the very מצוה *mitzvah* of ביכורים Bikkurim? *Bikkurim*, or the מנחה
Mincha. *mincha* of a בהמה *behemah*, the מנחה Mincha *mincha* that comes
with the מנחת minchat... נסכים *minchat nesachim*,
before the עומר Omer, *Omer* is brought. אם הביא פסול *Im hevi,
pasul*. And if you brought, it's invalid.
Now that's actually a little bit funny in terms of the ביכורים
Bikkurim *Bikkurim*, that if it's brought before the עומר omer; *Omer* it's
invalid, because you know the עומר omer. *Omer* does not really work
on the ביכורים Bikkurim, *Bikkurim*. The ביכורים Bikkurim *Bikkurim* I mean I
guess if the ביכורים Bikkurim, *Bikkurim* is wheat it does, but the
עומר omer *Omer*, but you could have ביכורים Bikkurim. *Bikkurim* that doesn't
have wheat in it at all. So applying that to the ביכורים
Bikkurim. *Bikkurim* is a little strange, we'll bracket that for now, but
certainly if you bring any of these other things before the עומר
omer *Omer* it's invalid because before the עומר omer *Omer* is brought,
you know, all of this is טרף *treif* food. It's חדש Chadash
*Chadash*, it's אסור aser. *assur* to be eaten. So if it's brought
in the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash* before the עומר omer *Omer*, it's invalid.
קודם לשתי הלחם לא יביא *Kodem l'Shtei Halechem lo yavi*, now before
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem, *Shtei Halechem* you should not bring it,
אם הביא כשר kosher? *im hevi, kasher*, if you bring it, it's
kosher. Now the simplest way to understand the difference between before the
עומר omer, *Omer* and before the שתי הלחם shtei halechem *Shtei Halechem*
and תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* points this out, is what I just said.
That before the עומר omer *Omer* it's טרף *treif*. Before the עומר
omer *Omer* it's חדש *Chadash* and therefore it's טרף *treif* and there's
a principle of נימאס ליה איסורא *nimasgei issur* as you might remember
that טרף *treif* food cannot be acceptable as a קרבן *korban* so
therefore before the עומר omer *Omer* it's invalid. After the עומר omer
*Omer* it's kosher and the עומר omer *Omer* was מתיר matir *matir*
the food, there's only a הלכה halacha? *halakha* that you cannot bring
in anything prior to the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem. *Shtei Halechem* because
the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem *Shtei Halechem* should be ביכורים Bikkurim, *Bikkurim*.
So there, okay, if you went ahead and you brought it even
though you somewhat compromised the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem *Shtei Halechem's* status
as ביכורים Bikkurim. *Bikkurim*, the קרבן *korban* is still kosher, that's not
as big of a problem as bringing טרף *treif* food. That's the
simple sense of this משנה Mishna *Mishnah* but we will look at
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* for interestingly the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to
have a real problem with this. So let's take a look at
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. So יתיב רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon וקקשיא ליה
*yativ Rebbi Tarfon v'kakashei lei*. So טרפון *Tarfon* was sitting and he
had the following difficulty. מה בין קודם לעומר לקודם שתי הלחם Shtei
HaLechem. *Ma bein kodem la'omer l'kodem Shtei Halechem*? What's the difference between
before the עומר omer, *Omer* and before the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem,
*Shtei Halechem*? Why before the עומר omer *Omer* בדיעבד b'di'avad *b'di'avad* is
it not good and before the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem? *Shtei Halechem*
and after the עומר Omer *Omer* בדיעבד b'di'avad *b'di'avad* it is good?
So אמר ליה לפניו יהודה בר נחמיה *amar lei lefanav Yehuda bar
Nechemya*. יהודה בר נחמיה *Yehuda bar Nechemya* had an answer. לא *Lo*.
No, it's not difficult. אם אמרת קודם לעומר שכן הותר מכללו hutar
miklalo, להדיוט *Im amarta kodem la'omer sheken hutra m'khlal l'hedyot*. Before the
עומר Omer *Omer* it's understandable why it's not good because even a,
you know, even outside of the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*, even a normal
person, a lay person can't eat it. So it has not yet
become permissible even to a lay person. But תאמר קודם לשתי הלחם
*tomar kodem l'Shtei Halechem*, would you say the same thing will be
true before the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem *Shtei Halechem* was brought but
after the עומר Omer. *Omer*? In that case שהותרה מכללה להדיוט *shehutra
m'khlala l'hedyot*. It would become- it's already been permissible to a lay
person. And since it's already been made permissible to a lay person,
it's understandable why it should be permissible in the מקדש Mikdash. *Mikdash*.
So that's why בדיעבד bedieved *b'di'avad* it's good after the עומר Omer
*Omer* because it's already become permissible to a lay person. So שתק
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon *shatak Rebbi Tarfon*. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon *Rebbi
Tarfon* was silent, he didn't have anything to respond, it was like
it was like a good answer and he couldn't respond to it.
So צהבו פניו של רבי יהודה בן נחמיה Rabbi Yehuda ben Nechemiah
*tsahu panav shel Rebbi Yehuda ben Nechemya*. So יהודה בן נחמיה Yehuda
ben Nechemya? *Yehuda ben Nechemya* was feeling very full of himself, his
face lit up, he felt very proud that he gave an answer
that רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon *Rebbi Tarfon* didn't have. So what happened?
So the story is not going to end well. אמר לו רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Amar lo Rebbi Akiva*. רבי Rabbi עקיבא *Rebbi Akiva*
said to him יהודה *Yehuda*, צהבו פניך שהשבת את הזקן *tsahu panekha
she-heishavta et ha-zaken*? יהודה *Yehuda*, you're so proud, your face lit up
because you had an answer to the elder? to רבי טרפון, Rabbi
Tarfon you gave an answer to this elder רבי and you feel
so proud. תמיהני אם תאריך ימים. Tamihani im ta'arich yamim. I would
be astounded if you would live many years. So you won't be
able to become a similar זקן zaken if you don't respect what
it means to be a זקן, zaken, presumably it means. אמר רבי
יהודה ברבי אלעאי Amar Rabbi Yehuda berabbi Ilai so a different רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה ברבי אלעאי Rabbi Yehuda berabbi Ilai said,
אותה פרק פרוסה דפסח היא, osa perek prasa d'Pascha hi,
that period was פרוסה דפסח, prasa d'Pascha, which means the two weeks
before פסח Pascha when everybody's learning the הלכות, halachot, that's why
they were
learning. כשהעליתי לעצרת, K'she'aliti l'atzeret, when I went up to ישראל Israel
in שבועות time, which
was whenever, which was nine weeks later or so, שאלתי אחריו, sha'alti
acharav, and I was asking for him, יהודה בן נחמיה היכן? Yehuda
ben Nechemya heichan? Where's יהודה בן נחמיה? Yehuda ben Nechemya I wasn't
able to find him. ואמרו לי V'amru li and they said to
me, נפטר והלך לו. niftar v'halach lo. He passed away. So you
see רבי עקיבא's prediction was right. So I'm not going to comment
on that whole little tragedy there about him being proud, which made
it inappropriate, but whether it warranted him dying at an early age
is another issue. But the question here
is what the heck is going on in terms of their halachic
issue? Like רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon didn't realize that before the עומר
Omer it wasn't כשר? kosher. And that תוספות Tosafot says, everybody says,
what's the big deal? Everybody can understand that before the עומר Omer.
it wasn't כשר. kosher, What was the big חידוש chidush of יהודה
בן נחמיה Yehuda ben Nechemya to come up with this answer that
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon could not realize?
Well, the question, why is it characterized רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon, response
that way? Because you have this all the time. Somebody asks a
question, somebody gives an answer, and you move on. You don't have
that whole issue about, right, that someone was silent? Maybe he was
so proud.
Oh and he was silent,
yeah, he was silent after he get the answer, right? But there
must be some attitude that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda had that's being
commented on.
Oh, you mean
back to the רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon part of this? Yeah. Oh
okay, I was talking just, I was bracketing the whole human aspect
and asking about the halachic aspect. But right, I mean, the fact
that, right,
a straightforward question and answer, we have them all the time.
Being silenced maybe means that even before his face lit up there
was something a little bit arrogant or disrespectful even at the time.
But also there's nothing strange about the question and answer, it's not
an unusual question or an unusual answer as far as that.
Well, but it's, I mean, but I mean, all
the time the גמרא Gemara will give an answer that a סברא
svara that makes a lot of sense.
Right, but when it says וקשיא ליה, v'kashya leh, thank you, I
mean, anybody could answer that question. What's the difference between the עומר
Omer. and before the שתי הלחם? Shtei HaLechem. Well, the עומר Omer
is not yet כשר, kosher right? It's not, the grain is אסור.
assur So the care is a question of characterization. Question itself is
not an unusual.
You mean if the question was more just the גמרא Gemara
of getting an obvious answer?
Yeah. I think the problem is the way it's described at the
outset of וקשיא ליה. v'kashya leh. Right, וקשיא ליה, v'kashya leh, he
was challenged with it. So right, so this is a real question,
why was he so troubled with this? And the תוספות Tosafot asks
the question, everybody asks the question. The best answer is in this
book, which was known as, I, this is from like 30 years
ago I found this, I dusted it off, it might have been
reprinted. It says שיטה להרשב"א ז"ל, Shita l'Harashba zal, it's like the
only ראשון Rishon other than תוספות Tosafot we have on מנחות, and
it was attributed to the רשב"א Rashba and there's no question that
it is not the רשב"א. Rashba. People think it might be the
תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid or somebody of his school. It's certainly somebody
that sort of is very creative and does not and thinks not
necessarily along the lines of like the other ראשונים. Rishonim. Anyway, he
asks this question, and here's the answer, and it's a great answer
and it goes to the core of what is how we understand
how the עומר Omer. and שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem operate. He says
of course you could understand the משנה Mishna, that the שתי הלחם
Shtei HaLechem. works because it makes it כשר kosher food, and then
the, actually, the עומר Omer. makes it כשר kosher. food, and then
the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem means it's the problem of let it
not being before the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem. it's not ביכורים bikurim,
and it's a problem, therefore בדיעבד bedieved it's כשר. kosher? But that's
not what רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon assumed. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon assumed
that the language is that the עומר Omer? is מתיר matir and
the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem is מתיר. matir So רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon understood that they're parallel. That the same way the food is
prohibited to a normal person before the עומר, Omer, the food is
prohibited to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. before the שתי הלחם. Shtei
HaLechem It's a מתיר, matir and until the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem
it's completely טריף treif for the בית המקדש. So that why was
וקשיא ליה, v'kashya leh, he took the משנה Mishna literally, and he
said if the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem wasn't a מתיר matir yet,
so what, okay, it's wonderful it's permissible to a lay person, but
it's still completely forbidden to the מקדש, Mikdash so why should בדיעבד
bedieved it be כשר? kasher. Because he took the משנה mishna. very
literally. So what was the response? The response of יהודה בן נחמיה
Yehuda ben Nechemiah, wasn't to say again what we said, no, one
is just about ביכורים bikurim. and the other about being טריף. treif.
He said I will accept your assumption that the idea is that
the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem it's really forbidden to the מקדש Mikdash,
and the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem. is a מתיר matir? and that
it does operate like that. But I'm going to tweak it a
little bit, and here's what I'm going to say. It's not a
new prohibition to the מקדש, Mikdash, there's one prohibition to an הדיוט
hedyot and there's another prohibition to the מקדש Mikdash and each one
operates separately. No, the prohibition to the מקדש Mikdash is an extension
of the prohibition to the הדיוט. hedyot. So when the grain becomes
חדש... it means that there's two implications: it's אסור assur to the
הדיוט hedyot and it's אסור to the מקדש. Mikdash In order to
make it permissible for the הדיוט hedyot you need the עומר; Omer.
in order to make it permissible for the מקדש Mikdash? you need
the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem So it is true the שתי הלחם
Shtei HaLechem is מתיר matir it, but it's a prohibition that it
shares with the איסור issur to the הדיוט. hedyot. And therefore his
phrase is הותר מכללו אצל הדיוט. hutar miklalo etzel hedyot. So once
this prohibition has gone through a stage of becoming lighter because now
it's been removed from the layperson, even though it remains forbidden to
the מקדש, Mikdash because the prohibition is not as severe anymore, it's
been weakened to some degree, therefore בדיעבד bedieved it will be כשר.
kasher. So that's a very beautiful explanation, A: what bothered רבי טרפון,
and B: רב יהודה בן נחמיה Rav Yehuda ben Nechemiah's answer about
הותר מכללו, hutar miklalo, which is not saying like, oh well it
was, you know, with a separate prohibition there, מעשר ישראל Maaser Yisrael
da da da, it is one prohibition but it became a little
bit less heavy, less severe after the עומר. Omer So conceptually what's
fascinating about this is, you know, תוספות Tosfos already says conceptually we
would have said no, there's no איסור issur to the מקדש, Mikdash?
there's an איסור issur. to הדיוט, hedyot, the עומר Omer. removes it,
the מקדש Mikdash? is an idea of ביכורים. bikurim. But the language
of the משנה says no, you need the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem
to מתיר it, there is an איסור. issur And they're saying so
that's the issue, if it has to מתיר it, why is it
כשר בדיעבד? kasher bedieved? And the answer is because it's one prohibition
that continues to the מקדש Mikdash but gets weaker after the עומר
Omer is brought. And so that's what he says, beautiful explanation. Now
we're going to go off.
Wait, before's the 'נפטר והלך לו', niptar vehalach lo, isn't that an
odd phrase? He died, what does it...
yeah I was thinking maybe it means he left town.
Well that would be very nice. I don't think so. I can
look for parallels. Having נפטר והלך לו niptar vehalach lo is
something not that it's a very unusual...
that he departed
and then he left.
And yeah he
died and he went to his עולם האמת. Olam HaEmes. I don't
know, I think it's a classic phrase. I can look from what
I remember, you know, it's used elsewhere. I think yeah, I can
double check. I think I've seen it elsewhere. I would, I will
check, but I think I don't think it is unique here. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay so אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak,
so רב נחמן בר יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak said, לדברי יהודה
בן נחמיה, le-divrei Yehuda ben Nechemiah, see לדברי רב יהודה בן נחמיה,
le-divrei Rav Yehuda ben Nechemiah, it's actually like they have different approaches
to how to understand this. So according to the approach of יהודה
בן נחמיה, Yehuda ben Nechemiah's נסוכי ביכורים שהקריבם קודם לעומר כשרים. nisuchi
Bikkurim she-hikrivam kodem la-Omer ksherim. So let's say like I mentioned this
in the משנה, the משנה mentioned ביכורים. bikurim. What ביכורים? bikurim. Wheat
ביכורים bikurim בדיעבד is not good, I accept. But there are other
things that are ביכורים, bikurim for example ביכורים bikurim, can come from
grapes. Let's say you took your ביכורים, bikkurim your grapes, you made
wine from them and you brought them to the מקדש Mikdash, before
the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem Okay, so what is their status? נסוכי
ביכורים שהקריבם קודם לעומר כשרים. nisuchi Bikkurim she-hikrivam kodem la-Omer ksherim. Those
are כשר. kasher. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously, that you know it's before... I'm
sorry, not before the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, before the עומר Omer.
they're כשר. kasher. So if you bring the new grapes and make
wine out of them and bring it even before the עומר Omer.
it's כשר. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously. מהו דתימא, Ma d'teima, I might have
thought, התם הוא דהותר מכללו אצל הדיוט אבל הכא דלא הותר מכללו
לא. hatam hu de-hutar miklalo etzel hedyot aval hacha d'lo hutar miklalo
lo. So why does גמרא Gemara think it's obvious? It's obvious they
were never forbidden based on the עומר, Omer so therefore they, you
know, even before the עומר Omer they're okay. So who cares? They
were never forbidden, it's grapes, it's not wheat. So no, I might
have thought the following: that when is the grain permissible before the
שתי הלחם? Shtei HaLechem When the עומר Omer had the effect of
making it permissible. It was הותר מכללו, it was forbidden then the
עומר Omer came and made it permissible. Then if you bring it
before the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem. it will be good. אבל הכא
דלא הותר מכללו לא, aval hacha d'lo hutar miklalo lo, here it
never, the עומר Omer had no effect on it. So if it
has no effect, maybe this new, the new grapes would be actually
בדיעבד no good if they were brought as wine before the שתי
הלחם. shtei halechem. So קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, it comes
to teach me,
כל שכן, kol she-ken, certainly, הכא דלאו איסורא כלל, hacha delav issura
klal, certainly the grapes are okay because it's true the עומר Omer
didn't make them permissible, but they were never forbidden based on the
fact that they're not new grain, they're new grapes, they're not new
grain. So what the heck is going on here? Meaning of course
these grapes were never forbidden based on עומר, Omer right? This is
not grain, these are grapes, right? They're something you're going to bring
as ביכורים. bikkurim So why would I have ever thought that בדיעבד
they're no good in the מקדש? Mikdash So again here this חידושי
הרשב"א, Chiddushei HaRashba, whoever it is, explains exactly the following way. He
says this is exactly the debate. If you're the רבי טרפון mentality,
so רבי טרפון thinks there's a parallel prohibition, there's a prohibition to
the מקדש Mikdash, and
there's a prohibition to the הדיוט. hedyot. They're different tracks but they're
parallel. One עומר Omer permits, the other שתי הלחם shtei halechem permits.
So he says okay, what types of things are forbidden to the
מקדש? Mikdash We know what's forbidden to the הדיוט, hedyot, new grain,
לחם קלי וכרמל. lechem kali ve-karmel. What's forbidden to the מקדש? Mikdash
Well the מקדש Mikdash, it's not about grain, it says that it
has to be ביכורים. bikkurim. So for... So for the מקדש, Mikdash.
any of the new produce is forbidden. So according to him, even
the grapes are forbidden of the new produce; it's a separate parallel
prohibition. And therefore, since they're forbidden, even if you know even before
after the עומר Omer. whatever, maybe they would remain forbidden. Okay, and
that's exactly what it's saying is that יהודה בן נחמיה's Yehuda ben
Nechemiah. response is. He says no. He says I don't agree with
you that they're parallel. I think the prohibition to the מקדש Mikdash
is an extension of the prohibition to the normal person. So therefore
it only applies to grain, it doesn't apply to grapes. So on
the one hand you רבי טרפון would say oh well the grapes
I can't allow, it never became permitted to anybody etc. You're bothered
because you think it's a separate prohibition, but if you think it's
an extension of the prohibition to the normal person then grapes were
never included in that prohibition so they're not a problem. Now it
still might be that you're not supposed to bring them before the
שתי הלחם. shtei halechem That's an interesting question. It could still be
that it still does somewhat impinge on the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
status as ביכורים, bikkurim but to think that there's a prohibition of
them to the מקדש, Mikdash that's not, the prohibition to the מקדש
Mikdash at most is only an extension of what is prohibited to
the layperson. Okay, now we move on. So that's a very fascinating
conceptual discussion of what is the nature of the forbidden of what's
forbidden to the מקדש Mikdash, before the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem, Is
it an independent track and it's everything in fundamentally forbidden and you
need the שתי הלחם shtei halechem to מתיר? That's what רבי טרפון
says. Is it an extension of what's forbidden to the הדיוט hedyot
and therefore would only be grain and that's you know what רבי
יהודה בן נחמיה says and therefore the prohibition is lighter when after
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem is after the עומר Omer is brought,
or is it not even prohibited at all? It's only prohibited to
the layperson. So the מקדש, Mikdash the only problem is don't bring
something new because it compromises the שתי הלחם shtei halechem status as
ביכורים. So really three very different ways of looking at it. Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara goes on, skipping the parenthesis, בעי רמי בר
חמא. Ba'ei Rami bar Chama. So רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama
asked שתי הלחם מהו שיתירו שלא כסדרן? Shtei HaLechem mahu sheyatiru shelo
kesidran? Can the שתי הלחם shtei halechem. operate in the reverse order?
First the שתי הלחם shtei halechem, and then the עומר. Omer היכי
דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? כגון דזרענהו בין עומר לשתי הלחם.
Kegon dezarnahu bein Omer leShtei HaLechem.
You planted grain between the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם. shtei
halechem. So the עומר Omer, wasn't מתיר it, right? Because it only
took root after the עומר. Omer וחל עליהו שתי הלחם, Vechal aleihu
Shtei HaLechem, it took root during this period of the ספירה, Sefirah,
and then when it came the שתי הלחם shtei halechem was brought,
it already took root, and the שתי הלחם shtei halechem? passed over
it, so it was brought when this stuff already existed and had
taken root. And then what happened? And then it was next year
פסח Pesach and now we have the עומר. Omer, So it's very
simple, right? You understand how you can have the שתי הלחם shtei
halechem and the עומר Omer coming out of order? The grain was
planted and took root before the שתי הלחם shtei halechem but after
the עומר. Omer So first it encountered the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem
then it encountered the עומר. Omer. Now I want to bring this
to the מקדש. Mikdash Am I allowed to bring this as grain
to the מקדש Mikdash because it had a שתי הלחם shtei halechem
and an עומר? Omer It just had it in the reverse order.
מאי? Mai? What's the law? כסדרן שריין שלא כסדרן לא שריין? Kesidran
sharyun shelo kesidran lo sharyun? They make it permissible when it goes
the normal order, not out of order? או דילמא שלא כסדרן נמי
שריין? O dilma shelo kesidran nami sharyun? Or maybe even if it
goes out of order it's also permissible? Now again, this works very
well according to the logic that we've laid out of יהודה בן
נחמיה. Where he says it's one prohibition, but it gets permitted to
the מקדש in two stages, right? It's the prohibition to the מקדש
is an extension of the prohibition to the הדיוט. hedyot. First it
gets somewhat alleviated through עומר, Omer and then it gets fully removed
through the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem So if you think about that
two stages to remove the prohibition to the מקדש, you're going to
ask, what if those two stages occurred in a reverse order? Will
it still operate? But this conceptually sees it as one prohibition to
the מקדש which is an extension of the prohibition to the הדיוט
hedyot but it requires two stages to remove it.
Okay, so אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so רבא Rava said תא שמע,
Ta shema, come and hear. ואם תקריב מנחת בכורים. Ve'im takriv minchat
bikkurim. Here's a ברייתא, braita, if you bring a
מנחת בכורים, minchat bikkurim, במנחת עומר הכתוב מדבר. beminchat Omer hakatuv midaber.
It's talking about the
עומר. Omer So היכן באה? Heichan ba'ah? Where does it come? מן
השעורים. Min hase'orim. So you bring it from the barley. Now by
the way, you might be surprised to find out that the תורה
Torah never says that the עומר Omer. comes from the barley. Okay,
so it says you shall bring, you know, when it says about
bringing the עומר. Omer והבאתם את עומר ראשית קצירכם אל הכהן, Vehavetem
et Omer reishit ketzirchem el hakohen, it says reap your harvest to
the priest, it never mentioned the barley. Okay, it just says you
bring the first of your cutting etc. We assume that it's barley.
Barley is the first thing that ripens, but the ברייתא braita here's
asking how do you know that the עומר Omer comes from barley?
אתה אומר מן השעורים, Atah omer min hase'orim, you say barley, או
אינו אלא מן החטים? o eino ela min hachitim? Maybe it's wheat?
רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, נאמר אביב במצרים ונאמר אביב לדורות.
ne'emar aviv beMitzrayim vene'emar aviv ledorot. That's an easy answer. It says
by מצרים, Mitzrayim, כי השעורה אביב, ki hase'orah aviv, right, because the
barley was still ripe and that's why it was not destroyed with
the ברד. barad. So and it says אביב, aviv, you know, ripe
or by the עומר. Omer מה אביב האמור במצרים שעורים Mah aviv
ha'amur beMitzrayim se'orim the same way אביב aviv by מצרים Mitzrayim refers
to the barley, אף אביב האמור לדורות, af aviv ha'amur ledorot, so
when you want to here bring this קרבן of אביב aviv of
the ripened grain, it means the barley. Okay, that's a nice explanation.
רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, מצינו matzinu here's why we know
that it's barley based on a parallel. מצינו יחיד שמביא חובתו מן
החיטין וחובתו מן השעורים. matzinu yachid shemeivi chovato min hachittin vechovato min
hase'orin. We know that an individual has an obligatory sacrifice from
wheat which is the מנחת...
what do you call it? The...
what's the individual's קרבן that's חובתו מן החיטין? chovato min hachittin? It's
not the... that's a נדר, neder, that's not a חובה. chovah. Hold
on.
The מנחת חוטא minchat chotei is the חיוב chiyuv of the individual,
but that's שעורים, se'orin, right? Hold on, I'm sorry.
מנחת סוטה minchat sotah is שעורים. se'orin. סוטה sotah is שעורים.
se'orin. The מנחת חוטא minchat chotei is... ואם
לא תשיג ידו עשירית האיפה סולת לחטאת.
ve'im lo tasig yado
asirit ha'eifah solet lachatat. No, no, I'm sorry, it's מנחת חוטא. minchat
chotei. מנחת חוטא minchat chotei doesn't have שמן shemen and לבונה levonah
but it is חיטין. chittin. Okay, so. The מנחת חוטא minchat chotei
is the obligatory one from חיטין chittin and the obligatory one from
שעורים se'orin is by the סוטה, sotah, so there's an obligatory one
of חיטין, chittin, obligatory one of שעורים. se'orin. וציבור שמביאים חובתם מן
החיטין. ve'tzibur shemevi'im chovatam min hachittin. And we know the ציבור tzibur
brings obligatory out of wheat because of the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem
So we know that מן החיטין. min hachittin. This... we... so therefore
we can assume by parallel מביאים חובתם מן השעורים. mevi'im chovatam min
hase'orin. They're also going to have an obligatory sacrifice from barley which
will be the עומר. Omer ואם אתה אומר בא מן החיטין, ve'im
atah omer ba min hachittin,
and if you're going to say that the עומר Omer has to
come from the... from wheat, so לא מצינו ציבור שמביא חובתו מן
השעורים, lo matzinu tzibur shemeivi chovato min hase'orin, we're never going to
have a barley sacrifice of the ציבור. tzibur. Okay, so that's again
not so persuasive but assuming that there has to exist a parallel.
דבר אחר, davar acher, here's another argument. אם אתה אומר עומר בא
מן החיטין, im atah omer Omer ba min hachittin, if you say
the עומר Omer is going to come from the wheat, אין שתי
הלחם ביכורים. ein shtei halechem bikurim. You can't have the שתי הלחם
shtei halechem as the first of the new grain in the בית
המקדש. It's not first, the עומר Omer will have come first. Now
as I said it's still a problem because it's still not ביכורים,
you know, it's still that the עומר Omer still does beat it
as the first of the barley. And by the way until you
bring the שתי הלחם shtei halechem it's equally forbidden to bring a
barley קרבן, a barley מנחה mincha in the מקדש as it is
to bring a wheat one. So the עומר Omer does already compromise
to some degree the שתי הלחם shtei halechem status as ביכורים. Nevertheless
the ברייתא braita here's saying it's much worse if something that's already
חיטין chittin has been brought then there's no way you can call
it ביכורים. Here at least we can bracket the עומר Omer and
acknowledge okay it's true the עומר Omer, was brought but anyway that
was only a barley sacrifice. So even though we don't allow any
barley before the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem nevertheless it's easier to bracket.
Okay, so but if you're going to say that the עומר Omer
is חיטין, chittin, then the שתי הלחם shtei halechem will not be
ביכורים. Now how does this prove our question about the things operating
out of order? ואי איתא, ve'im itha, if it's true דשתי הלחם
שלא כסדרן שריין, deshtei halechem shelo kesidran sharuyan, that you can permit
new grain in the מקדש when the... when the things happen out
of order, first the שתי הלחם shtei halechem and then the עומר.
Omer, So then he says I have an answer to this ברייתא.
braita. I can explain how it's possible to bring the עומר Omer
out of wheat and it won't compromise the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
status as ביכורים. How? Here's the status.
משכחת לה דמקרב עומר מהנך דאשרש קודם שתי הלחם ובתר עומר דאשתקד.
mishkachat lah demakriv Omer mihanach de'ashresh kodem shtei halechem u'vatar Omer de'ishtakad.
Okay so meaning here's what happens, I'm going to bring the עומר
Omer from the... from the grain. I planted
grain, tried to think about... I think it would be helpful if
I use this visual. Okay, this is the עומר Omer of this
year, this is what do you call for שתי הלחם. shtei halechem
So I planted grain here and it took root here. Okay, then
it passed the שתי הלחם, shtei halechem, it passed the עומר, Omer
so that's happening שלא כסדרה. shelo kesidra. Okay, so that's the question
of whether that's... that's going to be like permissible before the שתי
הלחם. Shtei Halechem So the גמרא Gemara is saying like this, so
if I have that grain that passed here the שתי הלחם and
now it's coming up to the עומר Omer and I'm going to
use this grain, חיטין, chittin, for the עומר, Omer okay, and what
am I going to use for the שתי הלחם? For שתי הלחם
I'm going to use grain that the things happen כסדר, kesidra, stuff
that took place here. So I can still argue that what I'm
bringing here the חיטין chittin is still ביכורים even though חיטין chittin
was brought here, why? Because this is still ביכורים in the sense
that this is from the new חיטין chittin and this that I'm
bringing here is from the old חיטין, chittin, old by defined by
the fact that you had the two things that... that already made
it permissible, right, and this is the new חיטין. chittin. So therefore
it must be and if your whole problem is how can you
bring a חיטין chittin here and without compromising ביכורים, I can if
you would let me go out of order. So it must prove
that we're not allowed... that out of order doesn't work. Okay, so
let's read that again.
So משכחת לה דמקרב עומר מהנך דאשרש קודם שתי הלחם ובתר עומר
דאשתקד mishkachat lah demakriv Omer mihanach de'ashresh kodem shtei halechem u'vatar Omer
de'ishtakad that from last year they took root after the עומר and
before the שתי הלחם like I said in the middle here and
then... coming back around, and the שתי הלחם and I'm bringing the
שתי הלחם מהן דאשרש קודם לעומר דהשתא mahan de'ashreash kodem la'Omer de'hashta
took root before the עומר ובתר שתי הלחם דאשתכחית u'batar shtei halechem
de'ishkacheit which is the classic time, like they took root after the
שתי הלחם before the עומר. Okay, so is that clear meaning if
I'm bringing the עומר from the stuff that grew here and coming
around, it's still last year's grain and if you let me bring
it because you say things work שלא כסדרן, shelo kesidran, then it's
defined as last year's grain as opposed to the stuff here which
would be this year's grain. So do you see it? That's a
proof that it doesn't work שלא כסדרן shelo kesidran or else you'd
be able to bring it. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מי
סברת ביכורים לפירקא אמרינן? mi savrat bikkurim le'pirka amrinan? What makes you
think that when we say that the שתי הלחם has to be
ביכורים it means the first of the new fruit and we can
define the stuff that grew in the middle there from last year
as the old fruit? No, למזבח אמרינן. le'mizbe'ach amrinan. It has to
mean it's not just the first of the new grain, but it
also has to mean that it's the first grain that makes its
way on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. והא אכליה למזבח מפרי דהאי שתא ve'ha
achlei le'mizbe'ach mi'peira de'hai shata and at the end of the day
according to your scenario that you said why don't I bring it
from the grain that grew here and came back around, it might
be true that what I'm going to bring from ביכורים is from
a different crop of grain, but nevertheless if you don't focus on
the crop of grain, you focus on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, we still
have a problem because the מזבח mizbe'ach at this stage still had
wheat. Now, of course, that's not a good answer because the מזבח
mizbe'ach always has wheat. The question always is which wheat? The old
wheat or the new wheat? So by saying oh no no, you
don't focus on the fruit then you're right, focus on the מזבח
mizbe'ach and there's still a problem but yes, but the only problem
is you call this stuff new wheat rather than old wheat. And
so רש״י Rashi sort of tries to finesse that. He says, oh
and it's still called new wheat because it came after, you know,
because
it came before last year's שתי הלחם but that was really sort
of the question we were asking all along. Anyway, that's the גמרא
Gemara says so we're not able to use that as a proof
of whether things work שלא כסדרן. shelo kesidran. That question still remains
open, but what we have found out is three interesting explorations about
how we know the עומר comes from שעורי. se'orei. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara goes on. So that was one question. Do the
שתי הלחם and the עומר work שלא כסדרן? shelo kesidran? And again
conceptually what's key here and this is really again this point that
this חידושי הרשב״א Chiddushei HaRashba made is that conceptually that treating it
as the way שתי הלחם allows new stuff to be brought on
the מזבח mizbe'ach is that it's two stages together with the עומר.
The עומר permits one, you know, sort of 50 percent, you know,
as one stage and the שתי הלחם is the other stage. And
then it's reasonable to ask can they operate if you get, you
know, in the reverse order. But it's very different from seeing that
the prohibition of שתי הלחם is independent of the prohibition of the
עומר or from seeing that one is a real prohibition and the
other is just an issue of ביכורים. This is really seeing it
as it is a prohibition but it gets relieved in two stages.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. בעי רמי ס״ח ע״א. Ba'ei Rami samech-chet amud aleph. בעי רמי
בר חמא. Ba'ei Rami bar Chama.
So רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked: שתי הלחם הנצה שריא
או חנטה שריא? shtei halechem hanatza sharya o chanata sharya? What stage
does the new grain have to be or fruit have to be
for the שתי הלחם to say oh well we've brought the שתי
הלחם this stuff was already around and therefore it cannot be brought?
Because we know by the עומר for example, grain that has yet
to take root, the fact that there was an עומר doesn't make
it permissible, it requires the עומר of the following year. So what
stage does the fruit have to be in? Because the שתי הלחם
also allows the new fruit to be brought, the ביכורים to be
brought, it's not just about the grain. So what stage does that
have to be? So is it הנצה hanatza the sort of flower
like the flowering or the חנטה chanata the budding of the fruit?
So the
גמרא Gemara says: מאי הנצה מאי חנטה? mai hanatza mai chanata? What
are you talking about the flowering or the budding? אילימא הנצה דפירא
וחנטה דפירא, ilima hanatza de'peira ve'chanata de'peira, if you mean the flowering
or the budding of the actual fruit itself,
השתא השרשה שריא הנצה וחנטה מבעיא? hashta hashrasha sharya hanatza ve'chanata mibaya?
If taking root is enough, when the grain has taken root, if
you imagine you planted a seed and it has some roots growing
out of it, it's nowhere near the actual fruit itself and nevertheless
that is enough to relate to the עומר or the איסור by
the עומר case. So when it comes to the שתי הלחם, who
needs the fruit to flower or blossom, right, you don't need the
fruit to begin? Now of course the difference is that there you're
dealing with a standing tree. So what stage are you going to
define if not the flowering of the fruit? So the גמרא Gemara's
has an answer. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא הנצה דעלה וחנטה
דעלה. ella hanatza de'ala ve'chanata de'ala. The flowering or the blossoming of
the leaves around the fruit, not the fruit itself, but apparently I
don't know, I've never looked at a tree like this but anyway
apparently before the fruit comes out some leaves come out of the
like place where you
look at fruit they have little leaves around,
right, but does the leaf emerge from the tree prior to the
budding of the fruit?
Okay, so
then it has flowers, flower comes like the cherry blossoms. First you
have the blossom, when that falls off then
the fruit comes, so okay, remains. Okay fine, so that's what the
גמרא Gemara's is saying. So the same The same way by grain
השרשה *hashrasha* is enough to say it sort of exists and relates
to the עומר *Omer*, by שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*, this should this
be enough, you know what stage is enough to say it exists
and relates to the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*? And is it the
flowering or the blossoming? But it's of the leaves, not of the
fruit. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says מי הוי כהשרשה או לא
*mi havei ke'hashrasha o lo*, is it like השרשה *hashrasha* or not?
Do you go by one of those stages? תיקו teiku, *Teiku*, it's
not known. Now again what's significant about this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
that it makes it clear, which is not explicit in the משנה
*Mishna*, although implicit a little maybe because of ביכורים *Bikurim*, that the
prohibition of bringing new stuff before the שתי הלחם *shtei halechem* is
not only about the wheat or grain. The prohibition applies even to
fruit, because it has to be ביכורים *Bikurim*, you don't bring ביכורים
*Bikurim* until then, even though the ביכורים *Bikurim* don't even go on
the מזבח *Mizbeach*, you don't bring any of the new fruit. And
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, for example, raised a question about the wine.
When can you bring from the wine from the new grapes? So
that is prohibited prior to שתי הלחם *shtei halechem*, but regardless, you
know, and again going back to the earlier issue, there's obviously no
prohibition of חדש *Chadash* applies to them. The general prohibition of חדש
*Chadash*, that's only, you can eat this stuff, the חדש *Chadash* is
only by grain. So here the prohibition of new fruit when it's
not grain clearly
is
on a separate track. Okay, and that's why the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
does say בדיעבד *bedi'eved* the new fruit that's not grain will be
kosher because it's not related to the prohibition of חדש *Chadash* in
any way. Okay, so בעא רב חנא *Ba'i Rav Chana*, so בעא
רבה בר בר חנה *Ba'i Rabbah bar bar Channah* ask, חטים שזרען
בקרקע *chittin she'zaran bekarka*, you planted your seeds, your wheat seeds in
the ground, עומר מתירן או אין עומר מתירן *Omer matiran o ein
Omer matiran*, does the עומר *Omer* make them permissible or not? Which
seems like a completely absurd question. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says היכי דמי
heichi dami? *heichi dami*, what do you mean, what are you talking
about? אי אשרוש *Ee ashrush*,
if they've taken root, תנינא tanina, *tanina*, we taught it in a
משנה *Mishna*. אי לא אשרוש *Ee lo ashrush*, if it hasn't taken
root yet, תנינא tanina, *tanina*, we also taught that. דתנן *Detnan*, we're
going to see in a משנה *Mishna* tomorrow, אם השרישו קודם לעומר
עומר מתירן ואם לאו אסורין עד שיבא עומר הבא *im hishrishu kodem
la'Omer Omer matiran ve'im lav asurin ad she'yavo Omer haba*, that if
they've taken root before the עומר *Omer*, then the עומר *Omer* makes
them permissible, then it's like they already exist as grain and then
the עומר *Omer* permits them. And if they only take root after
the עומר *Omer* is brought, then you have to wait until next
year. Okay, so we already know. What does the עומר *Omer* operate
on? It operates on the grain that's taken root. So what's your
question, what's the status of seeds that are planted? It's an explicit
משנה *Mishna*. So he says לא צריכא lo, tsricha, *lo tzericha*, here's
what you need it for, דחצדינהו וזרעינהו v'zarinhu קודם לעומר *de'chatzdinhu ve'zarinhu
kodem la'Omer*, you already have harvested
them and planted them before the עומר *Omer*, ואתא עומר וחלף להו
*ve'ata Omer ve'chalaf laihu*, and now the עומר *Omer* has passed, וקמיבעיא
ליה *ve'ka miba'ya lei*, and here's the question: מהו mahu, ללקוטי ומיכל
מיניהו *mahu lirkutei u'meichal minaihu*, can you pick them off of the,
out of the ground and eat them? So here's what you did.
You took your seeds from last year's grain. Now, if I have
my seeds from last year's grain, if I wanted to make this
into flour and eat it, can I eat it? Of course. It's
from last year, was already in an עומר *Omer*, I can go
ahead and I eat it. Instead of eating it, grinding it into
flour and eating it, what'd I do? I planted it in the
ground. And now, and now it's, and now comes along the עומר
*Omer*. Now, if I were to say has the עומר *Omer* made
it permissible yet? The answer is no, because it hasn't taken root.
But that's if I wanted to eat the new stuff that grew.
What I want to do now, if I were to go back
into the ground and dig up these seeds and eat them again,
okay, do you understand the scenario? If I had not done anything,
right, I of course could eat the seeds because the עומר *Omer*
came along and oh, actually I may have stated the case wrong.
It wasn't that
before I planted them, excuse me, before I planted them, they had
not yet been in an עומר *Omer*. This is new grain that
has not yet been in an עומר *Omer*. If I keep them
in my pocket and wait till the עומר *Omer* comes, then the
עומר *Omer* will make it permissible, I can pop it in my
mouth. But instead what I did was I put it in the
ground and then the עומר *Omer* came. So how does the עומר
*Omer* relate to it? If I relate to it as if, well
they haven't taken root yet, they might as well be in my
pocket, okay, great, grain from last year in my pocket, the עומר
*Omer* came, it makes it permissible. If however I relate to it
as no, no, no, they're already planted, they might not have taken
root but they're planted, they're part of the ground, the הלכה halacha.
*halacha* is then the עומר *Omer* doesn't relate to stuff that's growing
unless it's taken root and it's not permissible. So that's the question.
How much after they're in the ground can I still look at
them as if they are basically seeds in my pocket? So let's
take a look. Let's see that again. Okay, דחצדינהו וזרעינהו קודם לעומר
*de'chatzdinhu ve'zarinhu kodem la'Omer*, you harvested them and planted them before the
עומר *Omer*, so you, they have yet to become permissible, ואתא עומר
וחלף להו *ve'ata Omer ve'chalaf laihu*, and the עומר *Omer* came and
passed by them. וקמיבעיא ליה *ve'ka miba'ya lei*, here's the question: מהו
Ma hu, ללקוטי ומיכל מיניהו *mahu lirkutei u'meichal minaihu*, can I pick
them up and eat them? What do I say? כמאן דשדי בכדא
דמיא *ke'man de'shadi bekada damya*, is it like they're in a vessel,
meaning who cares they're in the ground? They're in the ground but
they haven't taken root, so they might as well be in a,
you know, be in a can. And if they're in a jar,
ושרינהו עומר *ve'shari'inu Omer*, then the עומר *Omer* made them permissible. They
were grain that has not yet had the עומר *Omer*, the עומר
*Omer* came, made it permissible, they might as well be. in a
jar, או דלמא, O dilma, or do we say בטלו לגבי ארעא?
batlu legabei ara? They've already been planted, they're like the ground, the
עומר no longer relates to them as food, now they're planted seed.
Planted seed that have not taken root, the עומר doesn't relate to,
so it's an interesting question. I plant these seeds, have they changed
their status, or can I still relate to them, you know, before
they've taken root as if they are, you know, as if they're
normal seeds, as if they're not yet planted, and will the עומר
make them permissible?
So that's one question about the ground giving it the potential because
if it's in a jar, it doesn't make any difference. You're just
saying the ground has...
But the ground, right, but the ground makes it worse, the ground
sort of puts it on a different track. Right, if it's in
a jar, it's food waiting for the עומר, and the עומר comes
and makes it permissible. If it's in the ground, so that sort
of frames it very differently. This is no longer food, this is
stuff that's waiting to grow. Waiting to grow, you need an עומר,
and you need it to taken root before the עומר can relate
to it.
Also, were they looking for a visible sign or is this like
a capacity?
Oh, how do they know about taking root? Right, so the גמרא's
Gemara going to describe that. They basically gave an amount of time:
two weeks, a month. There were different estimates, but yeah, there was
time, it was defined by time. Okay, so that's one question. Now
we're going to have similar questions about this, about these planted seeds,
whether they're still seeds or have they become part of the ground
and have a different status. So here's the next question. יש
להם אונאה או אין להם אונאה? yesh lahem onaah o ein lahem
onaah? Is there a prohibition of אונאה onaah or the laws of
אונאה onaah or not? אונאה Onaah are overcharging. If you charge, it's
not a limit on how much profit you can make, but it
is a limit on not charging more than a range within the
going rate. You're not allowed to overcharge based on the going rate.
There is no אונאה onaah by קרקע. karka. Actually, it was learned
from last week's פרשה, parsha, לא תונו איש את אחיו, lo tonu
ish et achiv, you know, במספר שנים אחר היובל. bemispar shanim achar
hayovel. The irony, though, is is that that's a negative prohibition of
אונאה, onaah, and basically we pro- and that's talking about selling land,
and for the most part, we only apply אונאה onaah to מטלטלין,
metaltelin, cattle and not land. Now, there's different questions about one issue
is whether you transgress by overcharging. The issue here about אונאה onaah
is less about transgressing, and it's more about do the laws of
אונאה onaah apply? The laws of אונאה onaah mean that if there
was an overcharge, within a certain range of overcharge, up to, like,
a sixth, you return the extra money. Beyond that, the whole sale
was void. So when we discuss, 'Is there אונאה onaah by land?'
we don't mean 'Do you transgress by overcharging?' but we mean 'Do
the laws of returning the extra money or or annulling apply?' And
the basic principle is there is not אונאה onaah by land. It's
learned out from a כלל פרט וכלל, klal prat ukhlal, from other
לימודים. limudim. But the logic also is, as we know, you know,
it's very hard to get an accurate value on real estate, and
real estate could have, you know, a value much more than its
current going rate, especially if somebody particularly needs that plot of land.
So there is no אונאה onaah by קרקע. karka. Okay, so now
the question is going to be: What if I'm not selling the
land, but I'm selling the seeds that I planted in the land?
Are they already considered like land and therefore there's no laws of
אונאה, onaah, or are they considered like chattel and there is laws
of אונאה? onaah? So let's take a look. היכי דמי? What's the
case? אילימא דאמר ליה שדאי בה שיתא ואתו סהדי ואמרי דלא שדא
בה אלא חמשה. ilima de'amar lei shadai bah shita va'atu sahadi ve'amri
dela shada bah ela chamsha.
You say to the purchaser, 'Oh, I put in, you know, six
units, whatever, קב kav of these seeds,' and then it turns out
that you only put in five. So you cheated him, and you
cheated him by, like, a sixth, which is the amount of אונאה
onaah that would lead to a nullification of the sale. והאמר רבא,
veha'amar Rava, so obviously there's going to be אונאה onaah there regardless
of whatever you say, כל דבר שבמידה ושבמשקל ושבמנין, kol davar shebemidah
veshebemishkal veshebeminyan,
anything that goes by measure or weight or number, אפילו פחות מכדי
אונאה חוזר, afilu pachot mikedei onaah chozer,
even if
the
overcharge was less than the normal amount, was less than the tolerable
amount. Normally the tolerable is a sixth. Nevertheless, the sale is annulled.
Okay, so why? Because he says once you are using a precise
quantitative measure, then it means exactly that amount. And anything that's beyond
exactly that amount difference is off bounds and has to be reversed.
So therefore, the גמרא Gemara assumed that's true, normally we normally, as
I said, we can tolerate up to a sixth, more than a
sixth you return, but when it's a precise amount, we don't. So
the גמרא's Gemara assuming here that the same thing that's true about
cattle, it'll also be true even about land. That even if you
were to consider these seeds land,
the issue about אונאה onaah is different when it's a either misrepresentation
or error in the exact measure. For example, if I say, 'I
am selling you an acre of land, this plot is an acre
of land that I'm selling it to you,' and then we do
the sale, we go and we measure, and we find out it's
only 0.9 of an acre. So it's not like, 'Oh, there's no
אונאה onaah by קרקע.' karka. No אונאה onaah by קרקע karka means
I gave you exactly what I said I'm going to give you
and the question is: Can we accurately fix the cost? But if
I actually gave you a different amount than I said and we
were precise in the amount, we said an acre and I gave
you 0.9 of an acre, don't start telling me אין אונאה בקרקע.
ein onaah bekarka. So the גמרא Gemara says the case cannot be
here that you, you know, numbered the amount and was less than
you numbered, then certainly there would be אונאה. onaah. So what's the
case? אלא דאמר ליה שדי בת כורא היא, Ella d'amar leh shadi
bat kora hi,
I said, here's this land I'm selling you, and by the way,
I planted the amount of seeds that were necessary. So I didn't
tell you a number, a quantity. It's been planted as is appropriate.
ואתו סהדי v'atu sa'adi came along witnesses ואמרו לא שדי בת כורא
היא v'amru lo shadi bat kora hi
that no, you actually did not put enough seeds in it, you
know, it was not sufficient. But it's not a number. So because
it's not a number, it's not an automatic ביטול מקח, bittul mekach,
and then the question becomes, is it chattel, which would have אונאה,
ona'ah, or is it קרקע, karka, which would not have אונאה? ona'ah?
So therefore here's the question: יש להן אונאה, yesh lahen ona'ah, is
there אונאה, ona'ah, כמאן דשדי בכדיא דמי? keman d'shadi bekadya dami?
Because since the seeds have not yet taken root and the cheating
or the, you know, was on the seeds, the seeds might be,
might as well just be in a vessel, so it's really chattel,
it's not land. They haven't taken root yet and essentially I cheated
you on seeds. The question is, did I cheat you on seeds
or did I cheat you on land? I'm selling you this plot
of land and I said it's been appropriately seeded, and it hasn't
been appropriately seeded, but the seeds haven't taken root yet. Right? Have
I cheated you on the land wasn't appropriate or have I cheated
you on the seeds? Okay, and that's the question. Do you treat
them as seeds or do you treat them as part of the
land? So is it like כמאן דשדי בכדיא דמי, keman d'shadi bekadya
dami, like they're in a vessel, יש להן אונאה, v'yesh lahen ona'ah,
and therefore laws of אונאה ona'ah apply, it's chattel? או דילמא בטלו
לגבי ארעא, od dilma battalu legabei ar'a,
or is it part of the land? So I didn't cheat you
on the seeds, I cheated you on the land and the land
does not have אונאה. ona'ah. Okay, so very similar question of we've
planted these seeds, they haven't taken root, are they still seen, are
they seen now as part of the land or are they seen
as separate from the land? Okay, so that's question number two is
אונאה. ona'ah. Now question number three: נשבעין עליהן או אין נשבעין עליהן.
nishba'in aleihen o ein nishba'in aleihen.
You cannot take a שבועה shvuah on land, you can only take
a שבועה shvuah on chattel. So I say I sold you this,
you say, I mean I say I bought this from you, you
said, no, you didn't, make a שבועה, shvuah, whatever the case is,
מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzat, some type of a debate that there's going
to be a שבועה. shvuah. We can't make it if it's about
land, we can make it if it's about chattel. So let's say
the debate is about, how did you give me the amount of
seeds I said I bought from blah-blah and they're in the land?
So is that a debate about land or is there a debate
about the seeds? נשבעין או אין נשבעין? nishba'in o ein nishba'in? Do
we say כמאן דשדי בכדיא דמי, keman d'shadi bekadya dami,
is it like they're in a vessel, וכמטלטלי דמו u'kemetalteli damu and
they're like they're chattel, ונשבעין עליהן, v'nishba'in aleihen,
you could take a שבועה? shvuah? או דילמא, od dilma, or do
we say בטלו אגב ארעא battalu agav ar'a that they're already part
of the land, וכקרקע דמו u'kekarka damu and they're like land, ואין
נשבעין עליהן v'ein nishba'in aleihen and you don't make a שבועה? shvuah?
So on all these questions, the גמרא Gemara says תיקו, Teiku, we
don't know. Okay, but an interesting series of three different questions. What
is the status of seeds that are planted before they've taken root?
Are they like they're separate from the land or not? And it
started with this interesting question about what happens when the עומר comes
around. And the עומר comes around and you treat them as though
they're food and they're separate from the land and the עומר makes
them permissible? Or at this stage are they already part of the
land and the עומר does not make them permissible because they haven't
taken root? Okay, so now the גמרא goes on.
Where were we?
One minute.
הדרתא לביתי, hadarta l'veiti, thank you.
Okay, so בעי. ba'ei. So now we have another interesting series of
questions starting with wheat but going to go far afield. בעי רמי
בר חמא: ba'ei Rami bar Chama: חטים שבגללי בקר ושעורים שבגללי בהמה
מהו? chitim shebegilalei bakar use'orin shebegilalei behemah mahu? Okay, not really about
חדש and עומר and שתי הלחם anymore, but we're talking about wheat.
So now we're going to say, let's say in your, in the
dung of your of your cows,
you find little, you know, there's still kernels of wheat there. You
can see them. You look at the dung, you can see undigested
kernels of wheat. Or undigested kernels of barley. What is their status?
רש״י Rashi says specifically it mentions wheat by בקר bakar because cattle
would eat wheat, other animals eat barley. Anyway, in the dung you
see undigested kernels. What's their status? Status about what's the גמרא going
to say? So the גמרא is going to say מהו, ma hu?
למי, lemai,
for what הלכה? halachic אילימא לטמויי טומאת אוכלין, ileima letamyei tum'at ochlin,
whether they can be considered like food to become טמא? tamei? Pretty
disgusting thought, but you want to pluck them out and wash them
and eat them. So and then something טמא tamei touches
it, it would be what? They do that with, really?
Coffee beans they get out of animal dung?
From one
particular animal.
Really? Why? Because somehow it gets certain certain coffee beans digested.
No, really?
Oh
my god, it's probably a delicacy that you pay extra for, right?
Okay, so anyway, you want to pluck them out and wash them
and eat them. Are they considered food or not? Okay, here they
are in the dung, are they considered food that they would become
טמא tamei for טומאת אוכלין? tum'at ochlin? So גמרא says תנינא, we
taught it in a ברייתא, braita, it's a תוספתא. Tosefta. חטים שברעי
בקר, chitim shebirei bakar,
the wheat kernels in the dung of cattle, ושעורים שבגללי בהמה use'orin
shebegilalei behemah and the barley kernels in the dung of other animals,
חשב עליהן לאכילה, chishevei aleihen l'achilah, if you're planning on eating them,
אין מיטמא טומאת אוכלין, ein mitammei tum'at ochlin,
just thinking is not enough to make them food. If they're there
in the dung, just planning on eating them is not enough to
change their status. However, לקטן לאכילה, liktan l'achilah, you plucked them out
of the dung with the intention of eating them, then they are
food, מיטמא טומאת אוכלין, mitammei tum'at ochlin, they become טמא. tamei. So
there you have it, that's the הלכה. halacha? If you actually do
some act to remove them from the dung, they get a status
of food. אלא, ella, so that's not our question. Our question is
tying it back to our מסכתא masechta למנחות. l'Menachos. I want to
now use these kernels and make flour out of them and use
it for a מנחה. mincha Is that appropriate? פשיטא דלא, pshita d'lo,
obviously not. It quotes a פסוק pasuk that it often quotes about
you know, certain things are just obviously inappropriate as קרבנות. korbanot. הקריבהו
נא לפחתך, Hakrivehu na l'pachatecha, is this something that you would bring
to your officer? הירצך, Hayirtzecha, would it find favor for you? או
הישא פניך, O hayisa panecha, would he lift up your your face,
would he show favor to you? If you wouldn't give this to
you know an important person, you certainly can't give it to God.
So it says, no, לא צריכא דנקטינהו, lo, tsricha d'naktinhu,
you take these kernels of wheat from the dung וזרעינהו and then
you planted them. And now you grew new wheat from them. What
is the status of the new wheat דקבעי לאתויי מנחות מיניה? d'ka
ba'ei l'asuyei Menachos minei?
You want to bring a מנחה mincha. from this new grain. מאי,
Mai, what's the law? משום דמאיסותא הוא, Mishum d'meisusa hu, was the
whole problem that they were sort of disgusting? וכיון דזרעינהו, V'cheivan d'zarinhu,
once they've been planted אזלה לה מאיסותיה, azlah lah meisusayih,
their disgustingness went away. Okay, that's just their past history but this
is a totally new thing. I mean first think about it for
a minute, we know you put a lot of dung into your
into your fertilizer stuff anyway, so you don't you know how finicky
can you be? This is no longer מאוס. ma'os. או דלמא, or
maybe this problem beyond them being disgusting. משום כחישותא הוא, Mishum k'chishusa
hu,
maybe the kernels that have been already digested and came out, I
mean they weren't digested, they were whole, but they went through the
animal and they came out, maybe then they don't have the same
potency. And therefore the grain that will come from them will be
of a you know substandard quality, will be weak. והכא נמי כחושן,
V'hacha nami k'chushen, here too the grain is you know less than
ideal, is weak. תיקו, so we don't know the answer. Now that
we're talking about things coming out through dung and do they change
status, we're going to be on dung for the rest of the
day.
בעי רמי בר חמא, Ba'ei Rami bar Chama, so Rami bar Chama
asked if you could just think about how radically we've changed topics.
But here's the thing you can sort of see exactly, you can
see how the דעת da'as connect. But here we are talking about
the status of things coming out as dung. Okay, בעי רמי בר
חמא, Ba'ei Rami bar Chama, פיל, pil, if an elephant שבלע כפיפה
מצרית she'bala kfifah mitzris that swallowed this basket called this Egyptian basket
which was made from what's it called palm leaves, okay, והקיאה דרך
בית הרעי v'hiki'ah derech beis ha're'i and it came out of the
opposite end, okay. So he swallowed and then it came out, he
excreted it. מהו, mahu? what's its status? Presumably we're assuming that it
still has its basket form on it. Does it still have a
הלכה Halacha status of a כלי, kli, of a vessel, of a
basket, if it went through the elephant? So מהו? למאי, L'mai, for
what
הלכה? halacha? אילימא למיבטל טומאתה, Ilima l'mivtal tumas'ah, to nullify its טומאה,
tumah, let's say it had had contact with טומאה, tumah, became טמא,
tamei, then it got swallowed and came out, is it a new
vessel or not? For example, I'll give you an example where something
is a new vessel. If you make a כלי חרס kli cheres
טמא tamei and you put it back in the kiln and you
refire it, it's like it's you made it a new and it's
it loses its טומאה. tumah. So maybe this is like a new
thing even if it looks the same. But the גמרא says no,
תנינא, we taught a famous משנה. כל הכלים יורדין לידי טומאתן במחשבה,
Kol hakeilim yordin lidei tumasan b'machshava, all vessels are considered vessels when
you intend, like if it's if it's the work is done on
it or could be done on it and you're the workman and
you decide that okay that's it it's ready to be used ready
to be sold, then it's defined as a vessel and can become
טמא. tamei. So that's its susceptibility to טומאה. tumah. ואין עולין מטומאתן
אלא בשינוי מעשה. V'ein olin mi'tumasan ella b'shinui ma'aseh. However once they
become טמא tamei they don't lose their טומאה tumah unless you actually
physically change them. And therefore the גמרא is assuming, which I don't
know why it's assuming,
that going through an elephant is not a שינוי מעשה. shinui ma'aseh.
It hasn't yet changed, nothing is nothing is physically different about it,
so it's going to remain טמא. tamei. So we know the answer
to that. So לא צריכא, here's our question, דבלע הוצם, d'bala utzam,
it swallowed you know
like what palm leaves, you know various types of like strips of
palm that are used for, what do you call those things that
you know you make
those accordion things for the לולב lulav out of? I mean they're
palm, they're palm leaves, but you know you have baskets, what are
what are those woven baskets made out of when they're made out
of, you know what I'm talking about? Yeah yeah yeah, those those
thick leaves anyway. Palm. I know but they gotta they gotta have
a word for that. Anyway okay, it swallowed that stuff, ועבדינהו כפיפה
מצרית. v'avdinhu kfifah mitzris. Okay and you now had, you went ahead
and you took this stuff that came out in the dung that
were these undigested palm leaves and you turned it into a basket.
So what's the question? Here's the question: מי הוי עיכול? Mi havei
ikul? Is it considered digested? And if it's digested then what? הוו
להו ככלי גללים. Havei lehu k'chlei glalim. If it's considered digested so
then what, here's the question, what material have you made your basket
out of? You removed these palm leaves from the dung of the
animal. What material have you made your basket out of? material have
you made it out of? Have you made it out of palm
leaves, or have you made it out of animal dung? How do
you define the material? And there's a difference, because something made out
of palm leaves is it can become טמא. tamei. A vessel made
out of animal dung is not one of the materials that can
ever become טמא. tamei. So the question is, the leaves that are
still there, undigested leaves in the dung, are they treated like dung
and therefore not a material that can become טמא tamei if you
make a vessel out of it? Or are they treated like leaves
and are a material that if you make a vessel can become
טמא? tamei? Are they like כלי גללים? k'khli glalim? We say כלי
גללים, k'khli glalim, the dung vessels, vessels made out of dung. By
the way, this is true, right, that they find in all these
archaeological digs that they had a lot of vessels that were made
out of dried animal dung. Okay, so there's even a word for
that, right? What is the word for, anyway, for that material? Anyway,
או כלי גללים, o k'khli glalim, או כלי אדמה, o k'khli adama,
or earthenware vessels. Now earthenware doesn't mean כלי חרס, k'khli cheres, that
does become טמא. tamei. תוספות Tosfos says this means that it was
made by sun-baked clay and not by kiln-fired clay. So that's another
type of a material that does not become טמא. tamei. But that's
not relevant, that's parenthetical for us. For us is the point that
dung vessels do not become טמא. tamei. So is it like a
dung vessel, ואין מקבלין טומאה, v'ein mikablin tumah, and does not become
טמא, tamei, דאמר מר d'amar mar because we've taught, כלי אבנים, k'khli
avanim, stoneware, כלי גללים, k'khli glalim, and dung, you know, dried dung,
וכלי אדמה, v'khli adama, and dried earthenware vessels, sun-baked earthenware, אין מקבלין
טומאה, ein mikablin tumah, do not become טמא, tamei, לא מדברי תורה
ולא מדברי סופרים, lo midivrei Torah v'lo midivrei Sofrim, not biblically or
rabbinically. So that's one possibility. או דילמא, o dilma, or do we
say לא הוי עיכול, lo havi ikul, it's not considered digested? And
it's not digested, and therefore you're really making it not out of
dung, you really made it out of, you know, palm leaves and
it does become
טמא. tamei. תפשוט לה tifshot lei מהא דאמר me'ha d'amar עולא, Ulla,
why don't we learn it out from what עולא Ulla says? משום
mishum רבי שמעון בן יהוצדק, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehotzadak, מעשה ובאו זאבים
שני תינוקות עבר הירדן. ma'aseh u'bau ze'evim shenei tinokot ever ha'Yarden. נבעך,
nebach,
there was a story where you had two wolves swallowed two infants
over somewhere in the, over the Jordan river and apparently they excreted
them. And now the question is, is the stuff that they excreted,
is that like the bodies and does it, is it טומאת מת
tumas meis or not טומאת מת? tumas meis? Is it like the
original bodies? ובא מעשה לפני חכמים, u'va ma'aseh lifnei chachamim, and it
came before the sages, וטיהרו את הבשר. v'tiharu es ha'basar. They said
that the flesh that they excreted of these infants is not considered
anymore human flesh, it's considered to have been changed and digested and
so on, and it does not communicate טומאה. tumah. So you see
once it's excreted, it's changed. Gemara says no, שאני בשר דרכיך, shani
basar d'rachikh, flesh is different, it's very soft. You know, here the
whole point is is that the palm fronds were not digested. The
flesh of course was digested, so that is considered something new. But
that doesn't explain our answer about the palm leaves. Says the Gemara,
ולפשוט מסיפא, u'lifshot m'seifa, how about trying to infer from the end
of that ברייתא? braisa? What does the end of the ברייתא braisa
say? וטימאו את העצמות. v'timu es ha'atzamos. They said that the bones
that were excreted are to have a status of human bones and
would communicate טומאה. tumah. So here these wolves, you know, excreted both
the flesh and the bones. The flesh did not have the original
status, the bones did. So why don't we see the bones as
an example where it does not change the status? So the Gemara
says no, שאני עצמות דקשי טפי. shani atzamos d'kashi tfei. That's the
other extreme. Bones are very hard, so obviously they don't lose their
status. The palm leaves, that's somewhere in the middle. They're not as
soft as the meat, they're not as hard as the bones, so
maybe their status actually would change. So you know, it's a little
bit, you know, interesting I think that we can take such profound
tragic human tragedy and issue and sort of analyze this at this,
you know, very sort of dispassionate way about the question about the
status. But that is certainly something that הלכה does. And the question
here is, you know, to what degree does this issue, does that
change its status? And the Gemara doesn't have an answer. תוספות Tosfos
leaves, tries to discuss a lot of other סוגיות sugyos in the
Gemara that raise questions about how digested things' status change, and actually
raises the idea that the point
that there are a couple of cases where it really matters, you
know, in practical case. For example, you open up a fish, let's
say a kosher fish, and you find inside of its stomach non-kosher
fish that it swallowed, small little non-kosher crustaceans that it swallowed. Do
they still have the status of crustaceans or are they now not
have changed because they've been consumed by the fish? And there it's
only in the stomach, it hasn't been digested, it hasn't come out
the other end. Okay, that's one example. תוספות Tosfos, also says you
shecht a chicken and you put it in your chicken soup on
Pesach, and then you find in its stomach little kernels of undigested
wheat. Is it חמץ chametz or not? Is it, so you know,
is it still have a status of wheat? So תוספות, Tosfos you
know, there it's not so clear what the answer is and there
are contradictions from different גמרות. Gemaros. And תוספות Tosfos says that we
should be as long as the thing still basically looks the same,
we need to be strict. תוספות Tosfos makes the obvious point that
the Gemara does not make, sort of little implicit in the Gemara
about talking about soft or hard, but תוספות Tosafot makes the point
that if it hasn't changed form, you know, then clearly we should
assume that it still has the same status.
Swallows a worm.
Right? Right, that's the case. Exactly, the worm. Right, so תוספות'ס Tosfos's
basic point is that
Not good or just? No, just that worm. Right. You remove the
worm. Exactly.
Okay. So now the גמרא has one more question. Let's... what? What
time is it? Is it 8:30 already? All right, let's try to
read one last question quickly. בעי רבי זירא, Ba'ei Rabbi Zeira, רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira asked. It's a crazy question. חטים שירדו בעבים, Chittim
she-yardu be-avim, if it rained wheat, okay? It didn't rain rain. So
רש"י Rashi says how did that happen? רש"י Rashi says well, maybe
I don't know, a boat with wheat got sort of sucked up
by some whirlwind and then fell back down. So תוספות anyway says
we're talking about דרך נס. derech nes. Anyway, so it rained wheat,
מהו? What's the law? למאי, Le-mai, what הלכה? אילימא מנחות, Ileima menachos,
can you bring a מנחה from it? אמאי לא? Amai lo? Why
not? It's wheat. What do I care where it came from? Now
that's because you can bring a מנחה from wheat even not grown
in Israel. So what do I care? Wheat is wheat. There's no
particular status for a
מנחה. אלא לשתי הלחם, Ella le-shtei ha-lechem, that has to come from
wheat that grows in Israel. So what's the status?
מאי? Mai? ממושבותיכם אמר רחמנא לאפוקי דחוץ לארץ דלא, Mi-moshvoseichem amar Rachmana
l'apukei de-chutz la-aretz de-lo, it says your where you inhabit means but
not outside of Israel. אבל עבים שפיר דמי, Aval avim shapir dami,
but the clouds, they're Israeli clouds. They're not outside of Israel. So
maybe that's okay. As long as it's not חוץ לארץ, chutz la-aretz,
it doesn't have to grow from Israel land as long as it
doesn't grow from חוץ לארץ. chutz la-aretz. או דילמא, O dilma, or
do we say, ממושבותיכם דווקא, mi-moshvoseichem davka, it has to come not
just not from חוץ לארץ, chutz la-aretz, but specifically from where you
dwell. ואפילו דעבים נמי לא, Ve-afilu de-avim nami lo, and even clouds
is not good, it had to really grow from the ground. Now
that's... it's a strange... besides that who knows what they were thinking
about with the cloud, it is a little bizarre that it thinks
that if it really thinks it somehow got created in the clouds
and came down, that that would be sufficient. Normally you need stuff
that's the produce of Israel itself and of the land. So the
גמרא anyway says it doesn't answer the question, but it ends by
saying, ומי איכא כי האי גוונא? u-mi ika ki hai gavna? Can
such a thing really exist, that it can rain grain? אין, yes.
כי דעדי טייעא נחיתא ליה רום כזבא חטי בתלתא פרסי, ki de-addi
taya nechisa lei rum kizba chitti bi-tlasa parsei, like this certain whatever
Arab nomad that fell down for him the height of a כזבא,
kizba, which is like either one or two טפחים tefachim high of
grain spread over three פרסי parsei of land. So yes, we heard
a story that somebody actually it happened, it rained wheat for him.
And that's why we're asking the question. Okay, where...